These days, it's tempting [music] to see
Britain's historic royal palaces as
monuments and museums.
Fair game [music] to be used as
backdrops for the telling of gory and
glorious tales from the past.
But while these palaces are no longer
lived in, they are still owned by the
queen.
Creators have to remember that the story
of a nation is also the story of a
living [music] family. And telling the
story inside their property requires
everyone to tread [music] carefully.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Q Palace, often overlooked by visitors
to Q Gardens, has been closed to the
public for nearly 10 years.
But a6 million pound scheme is underway
to reopen the Georgian hideway.
Part of Caroline Cliff's job is to find
artifacts and treasures to go on
display.
She's come to Kensington Palace to see
what's hidden away in the cellars and
vaults.
Time is pressing, but costume curator
Beatatric Balon has a suggestion to help
Caroline get ahead.
So, we keep this object in here with a
lot of other interesting things as you
can see. And I just likely want to check
it's the right way around, which it is.
And here it is.
I really don't like looking at it, but
we are going to display the head. You
might think this is a very frivolous
thing to have for a sort of series
museum and it's not a contemporary head,
but there exists a mask from the time of
George. I don't think it's his death
mark. That's why not
live mask.
>> Oh, it looks like his portrait.
>> Yeah, it does look like his portraits.
>> But I hate seeing it in that box. It's
just
[sighs]
>> George III is perhaps the best known of
Q's residents. So, if we just take
>> Beatatric has another very special
object to offer Caroline for the
exhibition. It's the waste coat worn by
George as a desperately ill old man
irretrievably out of his mind in the
last days of his life.
>> So, you wonder what the stains are,
>> don't you?
>> Yeah, you do wonder about that.
>> But, I mean, this is something that I
know we want to show,
>> especially as it's connected with that
late life, late part of the king's life.
So,
>> [sighs]
>> He was restrained [music] in the
straight jacket for long periods of time
and and sort of bullied into submission,
but they did what they thought was right
at [music] the time.
>> So, it's it's actually very sad object
to look at it.
Over two centuries later, there are
still sensitivities [music] around
displaying such deeply personal items
and
>> certain things you feel you shouldn't
almost maybe should not display. [music]
>> I know that I feel that sometimes that
it's so sensitive
that
>> I don't know you'd [music] have to think
twice about certain things. it.
Anyway,
>> Hampton Court has been a royal palace
since Tudtor times, but in 1737, George
III's grandfather abandoned it forever.
From 1760, the palace then became the
home of so-called Grayson Favor
residents. People of a certain class
received accommodation by the Grayson
favor of the monarch in return for
services rendered to the great British
Empire.
Sarah Parker is now at a late stage in
assembling the Grace and Favor
exhibition, but has hit one small
problem.
>> We aren't allowed to mention Grace and
Favor in a title. It is a quite a
controversial subject. Um, people being
granted free accommodation and and
seemingly, you know, for what for what
purpose? But it's very difficult to have
an exhibition and not refer to that
term. That's what it is really. It's a
historical term.
>> [music]
>> But though she's lost her cherished
title, at least Sarah's dream exhibition
still has a venue. Apartment 23, one of
the extensive Grayson Favor suites, and
Sarah loves it.
>> But what is remarkable about this
apartment [music] is that it's just like
a time capsule. It's almost like time
has completely stood still. [music]
And then through here is an amazing
bathroom. [music]
[music]
Kensington Palace is home to the Royal
Costume Collection and has been
displaying selected highlights for over
a century.
The most popular part of the collection
is the dresses that belong to Diana,
Princess of Wales.
Diana still evokes strong feelings.
Kensington Palace, the princess's former
home, became the focus of attention in
the days following her death, and 8
years on, hundreds still come to mark
the anniversary.
I am
>> research has revealed that Diana's
dresses remain the single biggest reason
for visitors coming to Kensington Palace
and a new Boulder exhibition is being
planned.
>> The Diana dresses are the main motivator
for the visitor clearly. Um so we need
to keep them on display for as long as
possible off display for the shortest
possible actually. That's that's the key
thing.
Nigel Arch, director of Kensington
Palace, is meeting costume curator
Joanna Marsha and director of
conservation John Barnes to discuss the
very particular sensitivities around
staging the new exhibition.
>> Our relationship with royal household
has to be good on so many levels. We're
running palaces that in the end are
owned by the monarch. The royal
collection um has huge numbers of its um
objects within the palaces that we look
after. So we have a very very close
relationship and then there are other
things that we want to get hold of so
that we can display them better for for
the public.
>> Another part of Kensington Palace is
also preparing for change.
>> John's keen to open more of the historic
rooms most recently used by Princess
Margaret.
>> He's hoping to tell more of the stories
associated with the apartments.
>> But what are the stories? Is there
something extra? Is there something more
they're going to get? That's the
question because if there is then it's
something that we will promote for next
year.
>> So it's the extent to which we would
feel we want to tell people about
[music] the life of the princess here I
suppose and how far you want to bring it
up to date. What are the sensitivities
and so forth and so on.
>> This question of the sensitivity is is
the key thing that we must consider.
>> The sensitivity here is that Princess
Margaret is not just a public nationally
known figure. um she's the sister of the
monarch. She's a real person and um her
death is not so long ago. So it's not
like for us talking about a figure in in
the dim and distant past. This this is a
very recent thing. And therefore, just
like with any other family, you would be
sensitive to how a member of their
family was talked about. part of the
deal has to be that we're going to be
careful about how we do that and that we
ask the family whether what we're doing
is okay by then.
>> But even though they're obliged to tread
carefully, the organization still has a
business to run.
>> The $64,000 question though is could we
promote it?
>> And and to promote it, there would have
to be an element of you're going to get
access to areas that you wouldn't
otherwise have. I think inevitably even
though we're trying to be sensitive, we
are slightly pushing at the boundaries
because um we want people to know about
the things that they can see and we want
to be able to uh market them.
[music]
Half the world away on the west coast of
Florida, a little piece of British
history is waiting to come home.
>> How do you feel about this? a little bit
nervous. Never know what to expect.
>> Beatatrice has been offered the loan of
a new item for the fourthcoming
exhibition of Princess Diana's dresses.
>> Oh, no. It looks very nice.
>> Oh, that's beautiful. It's nice to
finally see it after just seeing the
pictures.
>> Good condition.
>> Okay, it's my gloves that I brought.
So, this is a dress by Bruce Oldfield.
>> [clears throat]
>> and the princess wore it in 1990 1999.
The main worry with this dress for me is
because it's white that it might get
creased.
Try not to get my face anywhere near it.
[music]
[music] While the wedding of Prince
Charles and Camila makes headlines,
staging an [music] exhibition about
Princess Diana in Kensington Palace is a
deeply sensitive subject.
This dress has always been in private
ownership, [music]
and a lot of careful thought will be
given to how it would be presented in
the new exhibition.
But Beatatrice has another reason for
visiting Florida.
She's keen to visit the exhibition from
the Orthorp estate that everyone's
talking about.
This celebration of the life of Princess
Diana is being staged at the Florida
International Museum and is getting the
kind of visitor numbers most museums
dream about.
Before staging her own exhibition,
Beatric is [music] keen to discover the
secret of Florida's success.
When we went in, the lady said to to
some visitors, "This it's jam-packed at
the moment. I advise you to come a bit
later." And this room is really
jam-packed. So, did you have a lot of
lot of people coming in?
>> We do about 1,200 people a day.
>> A day.
>> A day. [music] Last weekend. We didc00.
>> The [music] photographs were taken by
her father as was the little movie.
>> Yeah. I mean that I [music] thought he's
obviously an inspired
>> Yes.
>> sort of film filmmaker really [music]
>> and this is a room that I personally
think is one of the saddest rooms
because you see the innocent girl and
then without really we know her future.
[music]
>> Oh this is incredible.
Oh wow.
>> What what is nice is having the plasma
screens [music] with film and
photographs of her wearing the dress.
>> We don't we [clears throat] have photos
but I would like to have more. Um and I
love these cases. I I was saying earlier
that I'm really interested in seeing
[music] these round cases. Round cases
are really great
>> because sometimes people write to us
[music] and say, "I can't see the dress
from the back, you know. Can't can't you
do something about it?"
>> Unlike the display at Kensington, the
exhibition is not just a display of
dresses, but the story of a life. It's a
powerful combination.
>> Box of Kleenex [music] in one of the
galleries all the time. It's the movies.
It's the music. the thought [music] that
we start when she was a little girl as
we were all little girls or had little
sisters and um but we know the tragic
end and [music] it gives a huge lump to
the throat.
>> The exhibition is powerfully emotive for
all who see it. I
>> think you were [music] really born to be
a princess.
>> This has inspired me to do good things.
Princess Diana, you will always be in
our hearts. You were such a great person
always. and then the name of the person.
>> We enjoyed this beautiful exhibit and it
truly did justice to the memory of of
Diana, a beautiful human being and now a
beautiful spirit.
>> Princess Diana, I loved all your
dresses. P.S. I do tap and ballet too.
>> Oh, that's sweet.
>> Macy 9 years.
>> The exhibition is very well done and
that was interesting to see. But what I
found most interesting is how people
behaved in the room. everyone stayed for
a long time that they really looked at
every single exhibit that
[clears throat] some of the rooms were
really busy. It's incredibly busy out
here at the moment. What kind of people
were and also what I found quite
interesting that despite myself I always
get quite moved quite moved by it. I
think it is it certainly does that it
does move you if if you want to or not.
It it sort of has has that effect.
In Hampton Court, there's another
problem for Sarah and her exhibition.
>> It's a bit of a problem at the moment.
Um, there's a possibility that we won't
be able to use apartment 23 as the
exhibition space.
>> Rot has been found in the wood that
could be dangerously weakening the
structure of the old building.
>> The experts have been called in, but
while they assess the extent of the
problem, Sarah has been banished to her
office. Personally, um I'll be really
upset that I really want to use the
department.
>> After many years researching the
exhibition, for Sarah, it's going to be
a long day waiting for news.
>> The experts quickly find the beast
that's destroying the delicate building
and Sarah's equally fragile dreams.
death watch beetle.
Actually,
let's watch Beetle and wet rock.
>> This timber is uh
structurally decayed to about 300 mm
from the from the from from the wall. In
this particular case, it's holding up
the floor that we're standing on. So,
obviously, it is important. Yeah, it
needs to be repaired.
[laughter] We shouldn't really be in
here probably.
Just testing with the resistor graph.
Now you look at the printer. You can see
it's completely hollow. That's not safe.
It's not structurally sound. It should
be. Should have a prop here to support
it. It's worse than all the beams.
>> The roof
>> for Sarah. It's been a long day.
>> It's been really nerve-wracking. I've
been trying not to think about it too
much and I've been trying to distract
myself so as I'm not thinking about it.
But
>> Sarah's been called to the apartment
together with the palace's great and the
good to hear the news from the experts
>> in the the first floor uh room here. Um
they found bad decay back to about 700
mm back from the the wall. As director
of conservation, John Barnes will need
to be convinced that the exhibition can
go ahead without risking damage to
either the fragile building or the
public.
>> We obviously have to make a decision in
relation to the exhibition we planned.
Um, but I suppose we ought to first of
all ask ourselves the question to what
extent this decay means there could be a
failure. And I'd particularly like to
see the bits that you can see with the
boards up. Right.
>> Okay.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Um, you know, discovery of this kind of
structural decay means that we just have
to address that first
>> in the corridor and underneath here.
>> Yeah, this would have been ideal,
>> but we're not going to be able to do
this right now. Then we've got to face
the decision about whether to carry on
with the Grayson and Favor exhibition
and if so where.
>> Yes, the project.
>> It's not good news for Sarah.
>> The Nameless exhibition is now without a
home.
>> Feedback is um apartment one above the
Kings um and areas of apartment 7.
>> Um and we've done some very preliminary
work and looking at a possible visitor
route. I think that's the only decision
we can make because the only other
decision would be to say let's stop now.
>> Absolutely.
>> And where we are and
>> it seems there is a chance of exploring
one alternative
>> but for Sarah it's definitely second
best.
>> I'm really really disappointed.
I don't want to talk about it.
The palaces are historic attractions,
but they are still the property of the
crown. At the Queen's discretion, a
number of apartments in Kensington
Palace are still occupied.
On the 29th of October, a day when the
palace would expect to be bristling with
visitors, rooms and corridors have
fallen silent.
Nigel Arch, the palace director, has
been obliged to display the greatest
sensitivity of all.
>> Well, it's closed. um has been since
Saturday as a mark of respect uh for
Princess Alice who who sadly died. Uh
Elizabeth was announced last Saturday
and she was the oldest royal ever and of
course the oldest inhabitant at
Kensington Palace. So it seems only
right that we should be closed for a few
days.
>> Princess Alice came into the royal
family when she married the Duke of
Gloucester in 1935.
Two months short of her 103rd birthday,
she lived in Kensington Palace for the
last 10 years of her life.
>> The part we're in now is run by historic
royal palaces. U we don't look after the
the private side as we call it. It isn't
a sort of, you know, isn't a museum. It
is a living royal palace. It's a place
where people live. Next door is like a
little village in some respects. And so,
of course, when the oldest inhabitant
dies, there is a great sense of loss.
And it's only right that we should we
should acknowledge that, I think.
Greenwich, Southeast London. Beatatrice
and conservator Janet Wood are still
unresolved as to whether or not they
should clean the stains from George
III's waste coat and have come to the
National Maritime Museum where a similar
problem was encountered with Nelson's
bloodstained uniform from the Battle of
Trfalga.
Beatatrice has arranged to meet the
International Authority on Nelson, Dr.
Colin White and textile conservator
Nicola Yates.
>> So that's the bullet hole up there, is
it?
>> Yes, that was where the bullet entered
um his shoulder and then traveled down
down inside.
>> I think the important thing to remember
about this coat is it's a national
iconic item. Everybody knows about
Nelson's coat and everybody comes to the
National Maritime Museum to see Nelson's
coat. Um, so we have had to against all
usual conservation practice to keep it
on display for a very long time indeed.
But I think it's also important to
remember that the whole costume, you've
got the stockings here, you've got the
britches, you've got the coat and the
waist coat, they all tell a story.
>> The blood stains on the stockings and on
the bottom of the coat are actually not
Nelson's. They are the blood stains of
his secretary who was killed on the
quarter deck of the victory just before
Nelson. the blood stain on the waist
coat, which we can't see here, but it's
behind the the bullet hole there, are
actually, we think, Nelson's.
>> Whoever, you know, whose blood it is
doesn't really make that much
difference.
>> I think people are quite disappointed
when we tell them that it's not his. And
and maybe we ought to show the waste
coat because we can be fairly sure that
the waste coat was his blood.
>> Why do you think people want to know
it's it's his blood?
>> Because um
it is an iconic item. Um, people come
here to see it because it expresses
something about the death of Nelson, the
great hero, in the hour of victory. And
so a sense of the blood stain is is
important, too. It's almost like holy
relics.
>> Nevertheless, there are significant
differences between Nelson and George
III. The noble death of an admiral doing
what England expects is a long way from
the somewhat taboo circumstances
surrounding the death of King George.
We have a taste and dignity issue. He's
in direct line to the throne and you
have living monarchs who who have a life
and who have their own sensibilities and
I don't want to sort of tread on
anybody's toes.
It's make orb breakak day for Sarah and
her Grayson Favor exhibition. John
Barnes has called a meeting in the
alternative venue. This is the last
chance for him to be convinced.
>> We might well pull it today because even
though the subject matter excites us,
where it is matters hugely. I mean, if
we can't get visitors to it or, you
know, if for some [music] reason the
story doesn't work perfectly within that
location, then it wouldn't be worth
doing it cuz these things are expensive.
And if we're going to do it, it has to
be done right. [music]
[music]
As you can see, [singing]
the views.
[music]
[singing]
We're sort of we're hoping that it can
be really really exciting and new and
innovative
>> and something very very different from
the visitor both in terms of how we're
telling the story and also in the story
we're telling.
>> You got the support of the group.
>> Great.
>> So well done.
>> Great great work. Now we can go back and
we can do the last bit of the experience
which is another Grace and Favor stare
>> down. We struggle.
>> I'm just relieved actually that the
exhibition is going to go ahead. I
thought at one point it wasn't going to
happen at all. Um, I'm disappointed
definitely that we're not using the the
other apartment, but um, no, I'm just
pleased that I'm still working on it and
the exhibition is going to happen.
Kensington Palace has reopened to the
public.
[music]
In the basement, it's time for Beatric
and Janet to put King George together to
see if the waist coat [music] fits.
It is heavy. It is heavy.
This is actually [music] a calico copy
of the actual waste coat.
This is made from exact measurements
taken from the [music] original waste
coat. So, it's the same size, it's the
same construction, it's not the same
fabric. Um, but at least it gives us a
good idea of the [music] size.
Though it soon becomes clear that George
won't be wearing the fragile waist coat
[music] in the exhibition after all.
>> From a conservation point of view, the
waste coat is not going to go on that
body for a start. It's much much too
big. First of all, there's there's a
there's a sort of ethical argument about
putting the two together because that's
the face of a relatively healthy
middle-aged man. And the waist coat
comes from a very ill old man. And if
you look at images of Jaws the third
when he's in 1820, he is very poorly
looking, very elderly looking, his long
white straggly hair.
>> He's all bent over.
>> And I think that would be almost
dishonest for visitors. I think the two
items displayed separately will tell a
better story than the two together. The
head on a small bust similar to this and
the waist coat um flat so that people
can get a relationship with both objects
rather than getting one sort of um image
all together. It's ready to meet its
public and people will be able to get
quite close up to it and they'll be able
to see it looking as if it had just been
taken off.
>> While plans to give greater access to
Princess Margaret's historic apartments
are finalized, there are dreams to open
yet another. But this might be the
greatest sensitivity of all.
>> But it's an amazing color.
>> Granting public access to Princess
Diana's apartments might remain a dream
for a long time yet. for any of us
working trying to explain history, um
the holy grail has to be to to to show
to talk about history in the places in
which it happened. And uh and for us
being able to do that to tell the story
of Princess Diana within an apartment
where she lived at Kensington Palace
would be a fabulous thing. But
realistically, I I can't see it's going
to happen in the short term.
However, the new exhibition of Princess
Diana's dresses will go ahead in
Kensington Palace in these rooms. It
will be a bright, airy transformation.
Like the Florida exhibition, it will be
a celebration, but there will be
differences in the palace's approach.
>> We don't want to have it so emotional.
Um, we do want people to see how
beautiful the princess was and what
wonderful dress she had, but we don't we
don't want to force them to have an
emotional response. So it it will look
very elegant um but there won't be music
and um it will there will be some
similarities but it will it will be
different.
>> Another exhibition allowing the public
to glimpse lives recently lived in the
palaces is being launched in Hampton
Court. In the palaces curators balance
unstoppable drive with absolute
sensitivity. And for some like Sarah it
pays off. The exhibition entitled
Suffragettes, Soldiers, and Servants for
Sarah is the culmination of over seven
years dedicated work in research and
therefore it must be a great highlight
of her life to see it all come to
fruition tonight. Sarah
[applause]
Um, I wasn't really sure it was ever
going to happen to be honest, but I'm
delighted that it's here. Delighted that
we finally opened the exhibition.
>> It's a lifetime lifetime's achievement
or um goal I should say. And I'm I'm
just so so chedd.
We've got lots of grandchildren up for
Grace and F residents, lots of children,
and so hopefully it'll be something for
them to to remember and treasure. So,
I'm speechless.
I can remember when most every [music]
night at 10 we sang an old refrain
as we wandered in the moonlight
[singing]
down Sunnyside Lane.
We heard the merry lock. And if the
night was dark, I'd steal a kiss again.
As we wandered in the moonlight
[singing]
some sun day.